Living with a physical disability isn't easy
العيش مع الإعاقة الجسدية ليس سهلا
anywhere in the world,
في أي مكان في العالم،
but if you live in a country like the United States,
لكن إن كنت تعيش في دولة مثل الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
there's certain appurtenances available to you that do make life easier.
هناك بعض الملحقات المتاحة لك لتجعل الحياة أسهل.
So if you're in a building, you can take an elevator.
مثلاً إذا كنت في مبنى، يمكنك أن تسخدم المصعد
If you're crossing the street, you have sidewalk cutouts.
إذا كنت تعبر الشارع، سيتواجد رصيف مائل
And if you have to travel some distance farther
و إذا كنت تريد السفر لمسافة أبعد
than you can do under your own power, there's accessible vehicles,
مما تستطيع تحمله، فهنالك مراكب يسهل استخدامها
and if you can't afford one of those,
وإذا كنت لا تستطيع تحمل تكلفة واحدة من تلك المركبات
there's accessible public transportation.
هناك وسائل النقل العام سهلة الاستخدام
But in the developing world, things are quite different.
ولكن في العالم النامي، الأمور مختلفة تماما.
There's 40 million people who need a wheelchair but don't have one,
هناك 40 مليون شخص يحتاج إلى كرسي متحرك ولكن لا يملكون واحدا
and the majority of these people live in rural areas,
وغالبية هؤلاء الناس يعيشون في المناطق الريفية
where the only connections to community, to employment, to education,
حيث طرق الوصول للمجتمع والعمل والتعليم،
are by traveling long distances on rough terrain
تكون عن طريق السفر لمسافات طويلة وعلى طرق وعرة
often under their own power.
وكثيراً ما تكون فوق طاقتهم.
And the devices usually available to these people
والأجهزة المتاحة غالباً لهؤلاء الأشخاص
are not made for that context, break down quickly,
ليست مصممة لهذا الغرض و تعطل بسرعة
and are hard to repair.
ومن الصعب إصلاحها.
I started looking at wheelchairs in developing countries in 2005,
بدأت أبحث في الكراسي المتحركة في البلدان النامية سنة 2005،
when I spent the summer assessing the state of technology in Tanzania,
عندما قضيت الصيف في تقييم حالة التكنولوجيا في تنزانيا،
and I talked to wheelchair users, wheelchair manufacturers, disability groups,
ولقد تحدثت إلى مستخدمي الكراسي المتحركة، والشركات المصنعة للكراسي المتحركة، وفئات الإعاقة،
and what stood out to me
وما لاحظته هناك
is that there wasn't a device available
هو عدم تواجد الأجهزة
that was designed for rural areas, that could go fast
المصممة للمناطق الريفية، والتي يمكن أن تسير بسرعة
and efficiently on many types of terrain.
و بكفاءة على العديد من أنواع التضاريس.
So being a mechanical engineer,
وكوني مهندسا ميكانيكيا،
being at MIT and having lots of resources available to me,
في معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا، ومع وجود الكثير من الموارد المتاحة لي،
I thought I'd try to do something about it.
فكرت أنني سوف أحاول أن أفعل شيء حيال ذلك.
Now when you're talking about trying to travel
الآن عندما تتحدث عن محاولة للسفر
long distances on rough terrain,
لمسافات طويلة في التضاريس الوعرة،
I immediately thought of a mountain bike,
فكرت فورا في الدراجة الجبلية،
and a mountain bike's good at doing this
والدراجة الجبلية جيدة في القيام بذلك
because it has a gear train,
لأنها تحتوي على علبة السرعات
and you can shift to a low gear if you have to climb a hill
والتي يمكن أن تنقل بها إلى العتاد المنخفض إذا كنت تريد صعود تلة
or go through mud or sand
أو السير على الطين أو الرمل
and you get a lot of torque but a low speed.
ويمكنك الحصول على الكثير من عزم الدوران ولكن بسرعة منخفضة.
And if you want to go faster, say on pavement,
وإذا كنت تريد أن تسير أسرع، على الرصيف مثلا،
you can shift to a high gear,
يمكنك استخدام العتاد العالي،
and you get less torque, but higher speeds.
للحصول على عزم دوران أقل، لكن بسرعات أعلى.
So the logical evolution here
لذا التطور المنطقي هنا
is to just make a wheelchair with mountain bike components,
هو صناعة كرسي متحرك بمكونات الدراجة الجبلية،
which many people have done.
والذي صنعه الكثير من الأشخاص.
But these are two products available in the U.S. that
ولكن هذان منتجان متاحان في الولايات المتحدة
would be difficult to transfer into developing countries
وسيكون من الصعب نقلها إلى البلدان النامية
because they're much, much too expensive.
لأنها غالية الثمن جداً.
And the context I'm talking about is where
والسياق الذي أتحدث عنه هو
you need to have a product that is less than 200 dollars.
أنك تحتاج إلى أن يكون المنتج أقل من 200 دولارا.
And this ideal product would also be able to go
وهذا المنتج مثالي حيث تكون أيضا قادرة على السير
about five kilometers a day so you could get to your job, get to school,
حوالي 5 كيلومترات يوميا حتى يمكن أن تصل إلى وظيفتك والذهاب إلى المدرسة،
and do it on many, many different types of terrain.
والقيام بذلك على أنواع مختلفة من التضاريس.
But when you get home or want to go indoors at your work,
ولكن عندما تصل إلى المنزل أو تريد أن تدخل إلى مكان العمل الخاص بك،
it's got to be small enough and maneuverable enough to use inside.
فيجب أن تكون صغيرة بما يكفي وسهلة الاستخدام بما يكفي لاستخدامها في الداخل.
And furthermore, if you want it to last a long time out in rural areas,
وعلاوة على ذلك، إذا كنت تحتاجها لتدوم مدة طويلة في المناطق الريفية،
it has to be repairable using the local tools, materials and knowledge
يجب أن يكون إصلاحها باستخدام الأدوات المحلية والمواد والمعرفة
in those contexts.
في تلك السياقات.
So the real crux of the problem here is,
جوهر المشكلة هنا حقيقية هو،
how do you make a system that's a simple device
كيف تصنع نظام جهاز بسيط
but gives you a large mechanical advantage?
لكن يعطيك ميزة ميكانيكية كبيرة؟
How do you make a mountain bike for your arms
كيف تصنع دراجة جبلية ليديك
that doesn't have the mountain bike cost and complexity?
بدون تكلفة وتعقيد الدراجة الجبلية؟
So as is the case with simple solutions,
وكذلك الحال مع الحلول البسيطة، لذا
oftentimes the answer is right in front of your face, and for us it was levers.
في كثير من الأحيان الجواب الصحيح أمامك،والذي كان بالنسبة لنا العتلات.
We use levers all the time, in tools, doorknobs, bicycle parts.
نستخدم العتلات في كل وقت، في الأدوات ومقابض الأبواب وأجزاء الدراجات.
And that moment of inspiration, that key invention moment,
وفي تلك اللحظة من الإلهام، لحظة الاختراع الرئيسية تلك،
was when I was sitting in front of my design notebook
عندما كنت جالساً أمام مفكرة التصميم
and I started thinking about somebody grabbing a lever,
وبدأت في التفكير في شخص ما يمسك العتلة،
and if they grab near the end of the lever,
وإن كان ليمسكها بالقرب من طرف العتلة،
they can get an effectively long lever
يمكن أن تحصل على عتلة فعالة طويلة
and produce a lot of torque as they push back and forth,
وتنتج الكثير من عزم الدوران خلال دفعها إلى الأمام والخلف،
and effectively get a low gear.
والحصول على العتاد المنخفض بفعالية.
And as they slide their hand down the lever,
وهم ينزلون أيديهم إلى أسفل العتلة،
they can push with a smaller effective lever length,
حيث يمكنهم الدفع بطول عتلة أصغر،
but push through a bigger angle every stroke,
ولكن الدفع بزاوية أكبر في كل تجديفة
which makes a faster rotational speed, and gives you an effective high gear.
مما يجعل سرعة الدوران أسرع، ويوفر عتادا عاليا وفعالا.
So what's exciting about this system
لذا الشيء المثير في هذا النظام هو
is that it's really, really mechanically simple,
أنه بسيط جداً ميكانيكيا،
and you could make it using technology
ويمكن أن تصنعها باستخدام تكنولوجيا
that's been around for hundreds of years.
كانت متواجدة منذ مئات السنين.
So seeing this in practice,
لذا فرؤية هذا عمليا،
this is the Leveraged Freedom Chair that,
هذا هو "كرسي الحرية المُساعد"،
after a few years of development,
بعد بضع سنوات من التطوير،
we're now going into production with,
نحن نعمل الآن على إنتاجه ،
and this is a full-time wheelchair user --
وهذا مستخدم دائم على الكرسي المتحرك
he's paralyzed -- in Guatemala,
إنه مشلول - في غواتيمالا،
and you see he's able to traverse pretty rough terrain.
وتستطيع أن ترى أنه قادر على اجتياز منطقة وعرة جداً.
Again, the key innovation of this technology is that when he wants to go fast,
مرة أخرى، الابتكار الرئيسي في هذه التكنولوجيا أنه عندما يريد الحركة بسرعة،
he just grabs the levers near the pivots and goes through a big angle every stroke,
كل ما عليه فعله هو أن يمسك على دعامتين بالقرب من المحاور ويدفع زاوية كبيرة لكل تجديفة،
and as the going gets tougher, he just slides his hands up the levers,
وعندما تصبح المنطقة وعرة أكثر، يرفع يديه لأعلى الدعامتين بسهولة،
creates more torque, and kind of bench-presses his way
لينتج المزيد من عزم الدوران، ونوعاً ما يدفع نفسه إلى الطريق
out of trouble through the rough terrain.
للخروج من المتاعب في التضاريس الوعرة.
Now the big, important point here is that
الآن الخلاصة الكبيرة هي أن
the person is the complex machine in this system.
الشخص هو الآلة المعقدة في هذا النظام.
It's the person that's sliding his hands up and down the levers,
الشخص هو الذي يحرك يديه صعودا وهبوطاً على الدعامتين،
so the mechanism itself can be very simple
لذا الآلية نفسها يمكن أن تكون بسيطة جداً
and composed of bicycle parts you can get anywhere in the world.
وتتكون من أجزاء الدراجات التي يمكن أن تحصل عليها من أي مكان في العالم.
Because those bicycle parts
لأن أجزاء تلك الدراجات
are so ubiquitously available, they're super-cheap.
متوفرة بشكل كبير لدرجة أنها رخيصة السعر جداً
They're made by the gazillions in China and India,
يصنعونها بأعداد كبيرة جداً في الصين والهند،
and we can source them anywhere in the world,
ويمكننا أن نجدها في أي مكان في العالم،
build the chair anywhere, and most importantly repair it,
بناء الكرسي في أي مكان، والأهم من ذلك إصلاحه،
even out in a village with a local bicycle mechanic
حتى في القرية مع ميكانيكي الدراجات المحلي
who has local tools, knowledge and parts available.
الذي لديه الأدوات المحلية والمعرفة والأجزاء المتوفرة.
Now, when you want to use the LFC indoors,
الآن، عندما تريد استخدام الكرسي في الداخل،
all you have to do is pull the levers out of the drivetrain,
كل ما عليك القيام به هو سحب العتلات من الكرسي،
stow them in the frame, and it converts into a normal wheelchair
وتخزينها في الإطار، وتحويله إلى كرسي متحرك عادي
that you can use just like any other normal wheelchair,
يمكن استخدامه تماما مثل أي من الكراسي المتحركة العادية الأخرى.
and we sized it like a normal wheelchair,
وقد جعلنا حجمه مثل الكرسي المتحرك العادي،
so it's narrow enough to fit through a standard doorway,
ليكون رقيقا بما يكفي ليمر عبر مدخل عادي،
it's low enough to fit under a table,
ومنخفض بما يكفي ليسع تحت الطاولة،
and it's small and maneuverable enough to fit in a bathroom
وصغيرا بما يكفي لدخول الحمام
and this is important so the user can get up close to a toilet,
وهذا أمر مهم حيث يمكّن المستخدم من الاقتراب من المرحاض،
and be able to transfer off
ويكون قادرا على الترجل منه
just like he could in a normal wheelchair.
مثلما تفعل مع الكرسي المتحرك العادي.
Now, there's three important points that I want to stress
الآن، هناك ثلاث نقاط هامة أريد أن أشدد عليها
that I think really hit home in this project.
والتي أعتقد أنها أثرت حقاً في هذا المشروع.
The first is that this product works well because
الأول أن هذا المنتج يعمل جيدا لأننا
we were effectively able to combine
جمعناه بطريقة فعالة،
rigorous engineering science and analysis with user-centered design
العلوم الهندسية الصارمة والتحليل مع تصميم يهتم بالمستخدم
focused on the social and usage and economic factors
يركّز على النواحي الاجتماعية وطريقة الاستخدام والعوامل الاقتصادية
important to wheelchair users in the developing countries.
المهمة لمستخدمي الكراسي المتحركة في البلدان النامية.
So I'm an academic at MIT, and I'm a mechanical engineer,
إذا أنا أكاديمي في معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا، ومهندس ميكانيكي،
so I can do things like look at the type of terrain you want to travel on,
حتى أستطيع أن أفعل أشياء مثل إلقاء نظرة علىنوع التضاريس التي تريد السفر عليها،
and figure out how much resistance it should impose,
ومعرفة مقدار المقاومة التي يجب أن تفرض،
look at the parts we have available and mix and match them
والنظر إلى الأجزاء المتاحة لدينا ومزجها ومطابقتها
to figure out what sort of gear trains we can use,
لمعرفة أي نوع من العتاد يمكن أن تستخدمها السلاسل،
and then look at the power and force you can get out of your upper body
ثم انظر إلى الطاقة والقوة التي يمكن أن تحصل عليها من جسمك العلوي
to analyze how fast you should be able to go in this chair
لتحليل مدى السرعة التي يجب أن تستخدمها في هذا الكرسي
as you put your arms up and down the levers.
عندما تحرك ذراعيك صعودا وهبوطاً على الدعامتين.
So as a wet-behind-the-ears student, excited,
كوني طالبا بدون خبرة كبيرة كنت متشوقاً
our team made a prototype,
فريقنا قدّم نموذجا أولياً،
brought that prototype to Tanzania, Kenya and Vietnam in 2008,
تم جلب هذا النموذج إلى تنزانيا وكينيا وفيتنام سنة 2008،
and found it was terrible
ووجدنا أنه كان فظيعا
because we didn't get enough input from users.
لأننا لم نحصل على معلومات كافية من المستخدمين.
So because we tested it with wheelchair users,
ذلك لأننا اختبرناه مع مستخدمي الكراسي المتحركة،
with wheelchair manufacturers, we got that feedback from them,
ومع الشركات المصنعة للكراسي المتحركة، حصلنا على تقييم منهم،
not just articulating their problems, but articulating their solutions,
ليس فقط للتعبير عن مشاكلهم، ولكن لإيجاد الحلول لهم،
and worked together to go back to the drawing board and make a new design,
وعملنا معا بالعودة إلى لوحة الرسم لإنشاء تصميم جديد،
which we brought back to East Africa in '09
والذي أعدناه إلى شرق أفريقيا سنة 2009
that worked a lot better than a normal wheelchair on rough terrain,
والذي عمل بشكل أفضل جداً من كرسي متحرك عادي في التضاريس الوعرة،
but it still didn't work well indoors because it was too big,
لكنه لا يزال لم يعمل جيدا في الداخل لأنه كان كبيرا جداً،
it was heavy, it was hard to move around,
كان ثقيلاً، وكان من الصعب التحرك به،
so again with that user feedback, we went back to the drawing board,
لذلك مرة أخرى بمساعدة تقييم المستخدم، ذهبنا مرة أخرى إلى لوحة الرسم،
came up with a better design, 20 pounds lighter,
جاء مع تصميم أفضل، أخف بـ20 رطلاً
as narrow as a regular wheelchair, tested that in a field trial in Guatemala,
كعرض كرسي متحرك عادي، اختبرناه في تجربة ميدانية في غواتيمالا،
and that advanced the product to the point
وتقدمنا بالمنتج إلى نقطة
where we have now that it's going into production.
نسير فيها إلى عملية الإنتاج.
Now also being engineering scientists,
كوننا الآن علماء هندسة،
we were able to quantify the performance benefits of the Leveraged Freedom Chair,
كنا قادرين على التحديد الكمي لفوائد أداء "كرسي الحرية المُساعد"،
so here are some shots of our trial in Guatemala
هنا بعض اللقطات من التجربة في غواتيمالا
where we tested the LFC on village terrain,
حيث اختبرنا قدرة الكرسي في تضاريس القرية،
and tested people's biomechanical outputs,
واختبرنا النشاط الميكانيكي الحيوي للأشخاص،
their oxygen consumption, how fast they go,
استهلاك الأكسجين، وسرعتهم في الحركة،
how much power they're putting out,
مقدار الطاقة التي يبذلونها،
both in their regular wheelchairs and using the LFC,
سواء في الكراسي المتحركة العادية وفي كرسينا
and we found that the LFC is about 80 percent faster
ووجدنا أن كرسينا المتحرك أسرع بحوالي 80 في المائة
going on these terrains than a normal wheelchair.
من الكرسي المتحرك العادي على التضاريس
and because of the mechanical advantage you get from the levers,
ونظرا للميزة الميكانيكية التي تحصل عليها من الدعامتين،
you can produce 50 percent higher torque
يمكنك إنتاج عزم دوران أعلى ب50 في المائة
and really muscle your way through the really, really rough terrain.
واستخدام عضلاتك لتشق طريقك عبر تضاريس صعبة جدا
Now the second lesson that we learned in this is that
الآن الدرس الثاني الذي تعلمناه هو أن
the constraints on this design really push the innovation,
القيود المفروضة على هذا التصميم دفعت بالابتكار حقا،
because we had to hit such a low price point,
لأنه كان علينا أن نصل إلى نقطة سعر منخفض،
because we had to make a device that could travel
لأنه كان علينا أن نصنع جهازا يمكنه السفر
on many, many types of terrain but still be usable indoors,
على أنواع متعددة من التضاريس لكن تكون قابلة للاستخدام في الداخل،
and be simple enough to repair,
وتكون بسيطة بما يكفي لإصلاحها،
we ended up with a fundamentally new product,
لقد انتهى الأمر مع منتج جديد جذريا،
a new product that is an innovation
منتج جديد مبتكر
in a space that really hasn't changed in a hundred years.
في مجال لم يتغير لمائة سنة.
And these are all merits that are not just good in the developing world.
وجميع هذه الأسس الموضوعية التي ليست جيدة فقط في العالم النامي.
Why not in countries like the U.S. too?
ولم لا في دول مثل الولايات المتحدة أيضا؟
So we teamed up with Continuum,
لذا نسقنا مع كوينتينيوم،
a local product design firm here in Boston
شركة تصميم منتجات في بوسطن
to make the high-end version, the developed world version,
لصنع النسخة الراقية، نسخة العالم المتقدم،
that we'll probably sell primarily in the U.S. and Europe,
والتي سوف تباع غالباً في الولايات المتحدة وأوروبا،
but to higher-income buyers.
لكن للمشترين ذوي الدخل العالي.
And the final point I want to make is that I think
وأعتقد أن النقطة الأخيرة التي تجعل
this project worked well because we engaged
هذا المشروع ينجح هو أننا أشركنا
all the stakeholders that buy into this project and are important to consider
جميع أصحاب المصلحة الذين يهمهم هذا المشروع،
in bringing the technology from inception of an idea
في جلب التكنولوجيا من الفكرة
through innovation, validation, commercialization and dissemination,
من خلال الابتكار والتحقق من الصحة، وتسويقها ونشرها،
and that cycle has to start and end with end users.
وأن الدورة يجب أن تبدأ وتنتهي مع المستخدمين النهائيين.
These are the people that define the requirements of the technology,
هؤلاء هم الناس الذين يحددون احتياجات التكنولوجيا،
and these are the people that have to give the thumbs-up at the end,
وهؤلاء هم الناس الذين يوافقون في النهاية،
and say, "Yeah, it actually works. It meets our needs."
ويقولون، "نعم، إنها تعمل بالفعل. إنه يلبي احتياجاتنا ".
So people like me in the academic space,
حتى الناس الذين مثلي في المجال الأكاديمي،
we can do things like innovate and analyze and test,
يمكننا أن نقوم بأشياء كالابتكار والتحليل والاختبار،
create data and make bench-level prototypes,
وإنشاء البيانات وصنع نماذج عالية المستوى،
but how do you get that bench-level prototype to commercialization?
ولكن كيف تحصل على نماذج عالية المستوى لتسويقها؟
So we need gap-fillers like Continuum that can work on commercializing,
لذا نحن بحاجة إلى الذين يملؤون الفراغ مثل كوينتينيوم التي يمكن أن تعمل على التسويق،
and we started a whole NGO to bring our chair to market --
وبدأنا منظمة حكومية كاملة لجلب حصتنا إلى السوق
Global Research Innovation Technology --
تكنولوجيا الابتكار والبحوث العالمية
and then we also teamed up with a big manufacturer in India, Pinnacle Industries,
ومن ثم تعاونا مع مصنع كبير في الهند، "شركة صناعات بينيكل"،
that's tooled up now to make 500 chairs a month
التي تصنع 500 كرسي في السنة
and will make the first batch of 200 next month,
وستصنع أول دفعة مكونة من 200 كرسي في الشهر القادم،
which will be delivered in India.
وستستخدم في الهند.
And then finally, to get this out to the people in scale,
وأخيرا، لإنتاج ذلك لشعب بهذا الحجم
we teamed up with the largest disability organization
تعاونا مع أكبر منظمة الإعاقة
in the world, Jaipur Foot.
في العالم، "جايبور فوت"
Now what's powerful about this model
الآن نقاط القوة في هذا النموذج
is when you bring together all these stakeholders
هو حين تجمّع جميع أصحاب المصلحة هؤلاء
that represent each link in the chain
الذين يمثلون كل حلقة في السلسلة
from inception of an idea
من بداية الفكرة
all the way to implementation in the field,
وصولاً إلى التنفيذ في الميدان،
that's where the magic happens.
هنا يحدث السحر.
That's where you can take a guy like me, an academic,
وآنذاك يمكنك أن تأخذ رجلا أكاديميا مثلى،
but analyze and test and create a new technology
لتحليل واختبار وإنشاء تكنولوجيا جديدة
and quantitatively determine how much better the performance is.
وتحديد أفضل أداء كمياً.
You can connect with stakeholders like the manufacturers
يمكنك الاتصال مع أصحاب المصلحة مثل الشركات المصنعة
and talk with them face-to-face and leverage their
والحديث معهم وجها لوجه والاستفادة من
and combine that knowledge with our engineering knowledge
والجمع بين هذه المعرفة ومعرفتنا الهندسية
to create something greater than either of us could have done alone.
لخلق شيء أكبر مما يمكن لأي منا القيام به لوحده.
And then you can also engage the end user
ومن ثم يمكن إشراك المستخدم النهائي كذلك
in the design process, and not just ask him what he needs,
في عملية التصميم، وليس مجرد سؤاله عما يحتاجه،
but ask him how he thinks it can be achieved.
ولكن اسأله كيف يعتقد أنه يمكن تحقيقه.
And this picture was taken in India in our last field trial,
وهذه الصورة أخذت في الهند في أخر تجربة ميدانية،
where we had a 90-percent adoption rate where people
حيث كان معدل تقبل الناس 90 في المئة
switched to using our Leveraged Freedom Chair over their normal wheelchair,
لاستخدام"كرسي الحرية المُساعد" بدلا من الكراسي المتحركة العادية،
and this picture specifically is of Ashok,
وهذه صورة لأشوك،
and Ashok had a spinal injury when he fell out of a tree,
وكان أشوك قد أصيب في العمود الفقري عندما سقط من شجرة،
and he had been working at a tailor, but once he was injured
و كان يعمل في متجر خياطة، ولكن عندما أصيب
he wasn't able to transport himself from his house
لم يكن قادراً على نقل نفسه من منزله
over a kilometer to his shop in his normal wheelchair.
على بعد كيلومتر واحد إلى متجره في كرسيه المتحرك العادي.
The road was too rough.
وكانت الطريق وعرة للغاية.
But the day after he got an LFC, he hopped in it,
ولكن اليوم بعد أن حصل على كرسينا جلس عليه مباشرة،
rode that kilometer, opened up his shop
وسار ذلك الكيلومتر الواحد، وفتح متجره
and soon after landed a contract to make school uniforms
وبعد ذلك حصل على عقد لصنع ملابس الزي المدرسي
and started making money, started providing for his family again.
وبدأ في الحصول على المال، ليعيل أسرته مرة أخرى.
Ashok: You also encouraged me to work.
أشوك: أنت أيضا شجعتني على العمل.
I rested for a day at home.
ارتحت لمدة يوم واحد في المنزل.
The next day I went to my shop.
وفي اليوم التالي ذهبت إلى متجري.
Now everything is back to normal.
الآن كل شيء عاد إلى طبيعته.
Amos Winter: And thank you very much for having me today.
آموس وينتر: شكرا جزيلا لكم على استضافتي اليوم.